Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union records, 1880-1990.
Congregational Library & Archives
Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union records, 1880-1990.
RG0122
Congregational Library & Archives
5.25 Cubic Feet
(6 boxes)
The first meeting of the Woman's Home Missionary Association was held on November 4, 1879 and the organization was formally chartered on September 28, 1881. The association was founded to support the needs of women and children and was supported by both individual membership and auxiliary groups. The association supported mission-based work in Massachusetts and beyond, especially in the post-war South. After the Massachusetts Congregational Conference merged men's and women's missionary work into the singular Massachusetts Missionary Society in the 1920s, the association was reformed as the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union in 1924. The union continues to operate today. This collection contains the administrative and financial records of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union and includes meeting minutes and reports, correspondence, ledgers, histories, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union
Woman's Home Missionary Association (Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union in May 1982; no accession number. Additional materials were donated by the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union in September 1995; 1995-03.
Historical Note
The first meeting of the group that would one day become the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union was held in the vestry of the Park Street Church in Boston on November 4, 1879. The following year, a constitution for the organization of women was adopted and the Woman's Home Missionary Association was formally chartered on September 28, 1881. The association was founded to "promote the spiritual and temporal welfare of those in need, especially women and children…" and the purpose of the association was "to engage all churchwomen in home mission work and to collect money towards that end." The group was supported both by direct membership and by auxiliary organizations, such as the Suffolk Alliance of the Woman's Home Missionary Association, throughout the whole of Massachusetts.
The Woman's Home Missionary Association was successful at raising funds, with annual gifts increasing from $2,500 in the first year to $29,000 in the tenth. The funds were used to support many initiatives and missionaries throughout the years. For example, the association supported Almira Steele's work in the post-war South as the associations first missionary, Lilla Davis and the Cotton Valley School for African-American women in Alabama, the Santee Indian School in Nebraska, the Tuskegee Normal School in Alabama, the Bethlehem Readers Home in Ohio, which later became Schauffler College and eventually Oberlin College, and the French Protestant College in Massachusetts.
The Woman's Home Missionary Association worked closely with the Massachusetts Congregational Conference during the association's early years. Then, in the early 1920s, the Massachusetts Congregational Conference merged the previously separate men's and women's missionary groups into the singular Massachusetts Missionary Society. Due to this merger, a Massachusetts court ordered that the bequests and money held specifically for women and children must be kept separate and administered separately from the Massachusetts Missionary Society. To adhere to this order, the Woman's Home Missionary Association was reorganized as the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union in 1924. By around 1927, many of the auxiliary groups previously associated with the union were moved under the umbrella of the Massachusetts Missionary Society.
The Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union continues to operate today. The union is affiliated with the Southern New England Conferences of the United Church of Christ and annually disburses invested income as grants from an endowment of over $1 million.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative and financial records of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The collection contains board reports and minutes, annual reports, by-laws and related founding documents, correspondence, grant records and correspondence, financial ledgers for internal finances, investments, and named funds, histories and biographies, newspaper clippings, addresses and speeches, and photographs.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the five series listed below. Series 2 and series 4 have been further divided into three and six subseries respectively. Series and subseries have been arranged chronologically. Materials within each series and subseries have been arranged in chronological order, generally, and by topic, when warranted.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1880-1988
Series 2: Financial records, 1881-1990
Subseries 1: General financial records, 1881-1990
Subseries 2: Bequest, trust, and gift records, 1892-1967
Subseries 3: Investment records, 1913-1986
Series 3: Histories and supplementary records, 1892-1982
Series 4: Grant and named fund records, 1896-1990
Subseries 1: Mary W. Hyde and Lucy H. Banister funds records, 1896-1903
Subseries 2: Grant records, 1898-1990
Subseries 3: General named funds records, 1903-1938
Subseries 4: Travis scholarship fund records, 1908-1982
Subseries 5: Joseph Hardy and Rosina Towne fund records, 1912-1933
Subseries 6: Golden anniversary fund records, 1925-1930
Series 5: Board of directors records, 1918-1990
Related Materials
Materials related to the Suffolk District, the successor organization of the Suffolk Alliance, and other similarly related materials, may be found within the Massachusetts Conference records, 1799-2012, RG5335, held by the Congregational Library & Archives.
Bibliography
"History." Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. Accessed March 28, 2025. https://www.mwhmu.org/history.
Charitable bequests.; Church charities.; Endowments.; Home missions.; Women in charitable work.; Women in missionary work.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-2024; Franklinton Center.; Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union; Northland College (Ashland, Wis.); Schauffler Missionary Training School (Cleveland, Ohio); Talladega College; Woman's Home Missionary Association (Mass.)
- Administrative records, 1880 1988; 1880-1988; 8 Volumes; 18 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the active day-to-day administration of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The series includes annual reports, correspondence, by-laws and other founding documents, documents related to the 1924 name change, secretary records, and insurance documents.
  - First annual meeting minutes, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Charters, constitutions, and by-laws, 1880 1957; 1880-1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1880 1983; 1880-1933, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Annual reports, 1880 1889; 1880-1889 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Annual reports, 1890 1899; 1890-1899 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Annual reports, 1900 1909; 1900-1909 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Annual reports, 1910 1920; 1910-1920 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Annual reports, 1921 1927; 1921-1927 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Secretary book, 1879 1881; 1879-1881 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Secretary book, 1881 1908; 1881-1908 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Annual reports, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports, 1956 1960; 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1961 1965; 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports, 1966 1970; 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1971 1975; 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1976 1980; 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports, 1981 1988; 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Agreement of association, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Suffolk Alliance of the Women's Home Missionary Association records, 1920 1927; 1920-1927 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Rhode Island neighborhood of auxiliaries sepparation, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Plan of work, 1924 1925; 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Name change documentation, 1924 1925; 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Annual report, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Suffolk Alliance yearbook, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Insurance documents, 1960 1987; 1960-1987 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Charter revival correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Financial records, 1881 1990; 1881-1990; 11 Volumes; 36 Folders
  This series contains records related to the internal finances of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The series includes ledgers, correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, committee minutes, and budgets.
  - General financial records, 1881 1990; 1881-1990; 8 Volumes; 16 Folders
    This subseries contains records generally related to the finances of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. This subseries includes ledgers, financial reports, budgets, auditors reports, and records of the finance committee.
    - Financial correspondence, 1881 1938; 1881-1938 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Finance committee records, 1897 1916; 1897-1916 (Box 4, Volume 3)
    - Finance committee minutes, 1897 1928; 1897-1928 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Ledger, 1918 1962; 1918-1962 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Financial reports and budgets, 1926 1959; 1926-1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Financial reports and budgets, 1960 1974; 1960-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Financial reports and budgets, 1975 1990; 1975-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Financial journal, 1938 1965; 1938-1965 (Box 1, Volume 12)
    - Cash book, 1946 1963; 1946-1963 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    - Cash book, 1964 1977; 1964-1977 (Box 6, Volume 2)
    - Franklinton center correspondence, 1951 1986; 1951-1986 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Auditor's reports, 1953 1967; 1953-1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Financial correspondence, 1960 1972; 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Financial correspondence, 1973 1980; 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Financial correspondence, 1981 1987; 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous financial records, 1965 1988; 1965-1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ledger, 1966 1985; 1966-1985 (Box 1, Volume 14)
    - Auditor's reports, 1968 1986; 1968-1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Income register, 1970 1977; 1970-1977 (Box 4, Volume 5)
    - Ledger, 1974 1985; 1974-1985 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Cash receipts, 1978 1981; 1978-1981 (Box 4, Volume 6)
    - Income register, 1978 1982; 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Cash disbursements, 1982 1988; 1982-1988 (Box 1, Volume 15)
    - Income register, 1983 1985; 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Bequest, trust, and gift records, 1892 1967; 1892-1967; 2 Volumes; 12 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to gifts and legacy giving to the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The subseries contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, wills and similar legal documents, ledgers, and a history of legacies.
    - Bequest envelopes, 1892 1938; 1892-1938 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Gifts ledger, 1898 1899; 1898-1899 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    - Bequests and legacies correspondence, 1900 1919; 1900-1919 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Bequests and legacies correspondence, 1924 1935; 1924-1935 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Bequests and legacies correspondence, 1936 1967; 1936-1967 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Bequest documents (S-Z), 1909 1951; 1909-1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Bequest documents (P-R), 1920 1927; 1920-1927 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bequest documents (A-N), 1917 1964; 1917-1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Probate court clippings, 1911 1942; 1911-1942 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Conditional gifts, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Conditional gifts ledger, 1915 (Box 1, Volume 11)
    - Sara P. Chamberlain trust, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bequest investment income receipts, 1928 1931; 1928-1931 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Legacies history report, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Investment records, 1913 1986; 1913-1986; 1 Volume; 8 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to investments held by the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The records include ledgers, newspaper clippings, reports on investments, lists of securities held, and documents related to stock transactions.
    - Stock transactions, 1913 1932; 1913-1932 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Chicago, Milwaukee and St. Paul Railway Company clippings, 1925 1932; 1925-1932 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Investments ledger, 1936 1984; 1936-1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Securities ledger, 1957 1969; 1957-1969 (Box 1, Volume 13)
    - Investments ledger, 1958 1986; 1958-1986 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Lists of securities, 1968 1977; 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Investments, 1972 1985; 1972-1985 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Lists of securities, 1978 1984; 1978-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Investments ledger, 1980 1986; 1980-1986 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Histories and supplementary records, 1892 1982; 1892-1982; 11 Folders; 1 Object
  This series contains histories, biographies, and other documents which document the history of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The series also includes newspaper clippings, anniversary programs, memorials, speaker lists, speeches and addresses, and a congratulatory letter from Jimmy Carter.
  - Clippings and newspapers, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sermons and addresses, circa 1892 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Copyright form, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Anniversaries, 1904 1930; 1904-1930 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Almira S. Steele biography, 1920 1921; 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Other women's home mission histories, 1928, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Memorials, 1929 1964; 1929-1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Speakers list, 1941 1975; 1941-1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - A Brief History of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Jimmy Carter congratulatory letter, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Kip Tiernan speech, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Embosser, undated (Box 4, Object 1)
- Grant and named fund records, 1896 1990; 1896-1990; 5 Volumes; 37 Folders
  This series contains records related to how the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union disbursed funds through named funds and scholarships as well as grants. The series includes ledger books, correspondence, and some histories.
  - Mary W. Hyde and Lucy H. Banister funds records, 1896 1903; 1896-1903; 2 Volumes
    This subseries contains ledger books related to the Mary W. Hyde and Lucy H. Banister funds of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union.
    - Mary W. Hyde records, 1896 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Mary W. Hyde and Lucy H. Banister funds book, 1897 1903; 1897-1903 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Grant records, 1898 1990; 1898-1990; 22 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to grants offered by the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The subseries largely includes correspondence but also includes photographs and documents describing the amounts awarded to various benevolent organizations.
    - Pledged work, 1898 1920; 1898-1920 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Talladega College photographs, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Grant correspondence, 1971 1972; 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Grant correspondence, 1973 1974; 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Grant correspondence, 1975 1976; 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Grant schedules, 1975 1983; 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Grant correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Grant correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Grant correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Grant correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Grant correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Grant correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Grant correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Grant correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Grant correspondence, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Grant correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Grant correspondence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Grant correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Grant correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Massachusetts Indian Association grant recipiant photographs, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Grant correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Congregational medical service car photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - General named funds records, 1903 1938; 1903-1938; 1 Volume; 4 Folders
    This subseries contains ledgers and histories for various and named funds controlled by the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union.
    - Funds account book, 1903 1916; 1903-1916 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    - Funds ledger book, 1906 1934; 1906-1934 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Administration fund books, 1909 1938; 1909-1938 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Fund balances, 1921 1938; 1921, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Story of the Funds", 1937 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Travis scholarship fund records, 1908 1982; 1908-1982; 8 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the Travis scholarship fund of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The records include correspondence, photographs, ledgers, and histories.
    - Edith Babcock Travis in memoriam book, circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Travis income fund, 1918 1921; 1918-1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Travis scholarship fund, 1920 1924; 1920-1924 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Travis memorial fund history, 1923 1965; 1923-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Travis scholarship fund correspondence, 1944 1957; 1944-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Travis scholarship fund correspondence, 1958 1965; 1958-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Travis scholarship fund correspondence, 1966 1982; 1966-1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Travis scholarship fund photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Joseph Hardy and Rosina Towne fund records, 1912 1933; 1912-1933; 2 Volumes
    This subseries contains records related to Joseph Hardy and Rosina Towne fund of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The subseries includes two fund books.
    - Joseph Hardy and Rosina Towne fund book, 1912 1916; 1912-1916 (Box 4, Volume 4)
    - Joseph Hardy and Rosina Towne fund book, 1912 1933; 1912-1933 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Golden anniversary fund records, 1925 1930; 1925-1930; 3 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the Golden Anniversary Fund of the Massachusetts Women's Home Missionary Union. The subseries includes correspondence and other materials related to the fund and fundraising.
    - Golden anniversary fund correspondence, 1925 1930; 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Golden anniversary fund records, 1925 1930; 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Golden anniversary fund materials, 1926 1929; 1926-1929 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Board of directors records, 1918 1990; 1918-1990; 13 Folders
  This series contains records by and about the board of directors of the Massachusetts Woman's Home Missionary Union. The series includes board of directors meeting minutes, agendas, officer lists, and the records of a nominating committee.
  - Board of directors minutes, 1918 1922; 1918-1922 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1923 1925; 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1934 1944; 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1945 1954; 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1955 1964; 1955-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1965 1970; 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1972 1980; 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Board of directors minutes, 1981 1990; 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Officers lists, 1928 1959; 1928-1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Officers lists, 1960 1989; 1960-1989 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Officers lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Board agendas, 1937 1990; 1937-1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Nominating committee records, 1970 1987; 1970-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)